Francis Bosworth papers, 1933-1982
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
Francis Bosworth papers
1933-1982
1933-1943
C0220
George Mason University. Libraries. Special Collections & Archives
0.5 linear feet (1 box)
The Francis Bosworth papers contain personal papers collected by Bosworth from the 1930s to the 1980s. About three-fourths of the material in this collection is about the Federal Theatre Project, other material consists of projects Bosworth worked on for the World's Fair in New York City in 1940, the National Council of Teachers of English 27th annual meeting, a "Report of an Experiment in the use of Documentary Playwriting for the teaching of Intercultural Education carried on in Selected Secondary Schools of Westchester County," and correspondence and papers about non-Federal Theatre Project employment.
Francis Bosworth
Biographical note
Francis Bosworth was born in St. Paul Minnesota on November 6, 1904. He attended the University of Minnesota before moving to New York City in 1929. In New York he was the author of several plays, the Head of the Drama Department of the New College at Columbia, and was the Director of the National Play Bureau of the Federal Theatre Project.
The Federal Theatre Project was a division of the Works Progress Administration (WPA), which provided employment for large numbers of artists, writers, and performers during the Great Depression (1929-1939). The Federal Theatre began in 1935 and, until its end in 1939, flourished as the first and only federally sponsored and subsidized theater program in the United States. Directed by Hallie Flanagan (1880-1969), it was a way for theatrical professionals to gain employment during the Depression.
Related Material
The Works Progress Administration oral histories collection, the Federal Theatre Project collection, the Federal Theatre Project photograph collection, as well as numerous other personal papers.
Scope and Content
The Francis Bosworth papers contain personal papers collected by Bosworth from the 1930s to the 1980s. About three-fourths of the material in this collection is about the Federal Theatre Project, other material consists of projects Bosworth worked on for the World's Fair in New York City in 1940, the National Council of Teachers of English 27th annual meeting, a Report of an Experiment in the use of Documentary Playwriting for the teaching of Intercultural Education carried on in Selected Secondary Schools of Westchester County, and correspondence and papers about non-Federal Theatre Project employment. Federal Theatre Project material includes correspondence, memorandums, material on the production It Can't Happen Here, articles written by Bosworth, a radio script, and a collection of National Youth Administration letters.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Francis Bosworth to Special Collections and Archives on October 21, 1978.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Federal Theatre Project (U.S.)
Subjects:
New Deal, 1933-1939.; Theater--United States.
Contents List
- Francis Bosworth papers, 1933-1982
  - Correspondence between Bosworth and Temple University, 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence between Bosworth and RCA, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Victory co-plan
  - Federal Theatre Project, March 20, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Christ in Concrete radio script
  - Federal Theatre Project, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Correspondence and memorandums (original and photocopies)
  - Federal Theatre Project, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Correspondence, assignments, papers
  - Federal Theatre Project, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    National youth administration letters
  - Federal Theatre Project, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Newspaper clippings
  - Federal Theatre Project, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Pittsburgh theatre; It Can't Happen Here; 80,000 theatres article
  - Historical Society of Pennsylvania speech, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - National Council of Teachers of English 27th annual meeting, November 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Synopsis of Rachel Davis DuBois's autobiography, March 1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Personal papers and correspondence relating to non Federal Theatre Project employment, 1933-1943 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Report of an experiment: Documentary playwriting as a technique of intercultural education, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - World's Fair - American common, 1940 (Box 1, Folder 14)